Finding Aid for William D. Revelli Papers 1907-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William D. Revelli Papers 1907-1994, 1935-1991
Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-
(in 10 boxes)
9 linear feet
Conductor of bands and professor of wind instruments at the University of Michigan. The series in the collection include: Biographical/Personal information; Correspondence, 1921-1994; University of Michigan Activities (primarily relating to performances and tours of the Marching Band and the Symphony Band); Other Professional Activities (relating to Band Conductors Conferences and band clinics, and including files of Revelli's writings and musical compositions); Visual Materials; and Sound Recordings.
9622 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the William D. Revelli Family (Donor No. 7024 ) and came to the library in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
William D. Revelli, "the Chief" to his many students, was born in Spring Gulch, Colorado, February 1902. The son of Italian immigrants, Giovanni (later anglicized to John) and Rose Bonino, William Donald was the third of seven children. In 1904, John moved his family to Illinois to take a position as a mine foreman in Panama.
Revelli began to play the violin after age 5 years. (Gregory Talford. "William D. Revelli: An Introspective Study," Masters Thesis 1985, p. 6; hereafter Talford [Catalogued separately]). After graduating from high school in 1918, Revelli went to college at the Chicago Musical College. He studied the violin under Leon Sametini, and trained for a career playing in the orchestras of the movie theaters of Chicago. (Talford, p.12) In 1922, Revelli was awarded a bachelor of music degree in violin performance. The following year he married Mary Endrietto Vidano. She remained with Revelli until her death in 1992.
Upon graduation, Revelli enrolled in the Columbia School of Music in Chicago in music education. He did his student teaching at the elementary and junior high school levels, and received a degree in public school music in 1925. (Talford, 16) Following his graduation, Revelli attended the Vander Cook School of Directing.
Revelli accepted the position of high school band director of Hobart High School Band, Hobart, Indiana, in 1925. The band began with three instruments. Revelli brought the number to twenty-two members by the time of their first concert in January 1926. (Hobart Gazette, July 1, 1981; Box 2) Four years later, Hobart High School Band captured the Indiana Class "B" band championship. By the time Revelli left Hobart in 1935, the band was seventy pieces strong. He frequented Hobart often, giving guest appearances and encouragement to the band over the years. (Hobart Gazette, July 1, 1981; Box 2)
Revelli was hired as Conductor of Bands and Assistant Professor of Wind Instruments by the University of Michigan in 1935. Edwin Franko Goldman once said to the band members, "Give him your whole-hearted support, and Michigan's band will be the finest of its kind in the world." (University of Michigan, "25 Years of Leadership," Pamphlet in 25th Anniversary Friendship Book, p. 2; Box 1)
"William's musicianship, dedication, drive and energy have become recognized by virtually every honor the band world could bestow on the University of Michigan." ("25 Years of Leadership," p. 2) Revelli inspired awe, fear, and determination in his students. Someone once suggested that the essence of true leadership was the ability to inspire others to want to follow.
Revelli was once asked to describe his amazing capacity for teaching others about music. "My first teaching point has nothing to do with the instrument; it starts out with attitude. What is attitude? Attitude starts with interest, enthusiasm, dedication, cooperation, and outlook. The conductor has a responsibility to create an attitude of love for music. You are not a conductor of bands, you're a conductor of people." (Talford, p. 276-77)
The two tours the University of Michigan's Symphony Band gave in 1961 and 1971 were probably the two crowning achievements in Revelli's career. In 1961, Revelli led the University of Michigan's Symphony Band on a goodwill tour of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. At the height of the Cold War, the response to the tour by the Soviet people was tremendous. Appearances were sold out throughout the tour. People commented on how outstanding the University Symphony performed at every location. No one had ever heard a band of this type performing so flawlessly. The caliber of each performance was outstanding. (Talford, p. 169)
Revelli officially retired as Conductor of Bands in 1971. He appeared frequently with the University Marching Band until his death in 1994. Revelli Hall was dedicated on October 20, 1973 to honor the man who made the University of Michigan's Marching Band one of the premier bands in the country. In the last years of his life, Revelli appeared in as many as one hundred guest conductor assignments each year. Even 1994, the year of his death, saw Revelli conducting several performances.
Revelli's contributions to his profession and his awards were numerous, including: president of the American Bandmasters Association; founder and president, and honorary life president of the College Band Directors National Association; a member of the screening committee of the music advisory panel of the American National Theater and Academy; Honorary National Grand President of Kappa Kappa Psi, honorary band fraternity; John Philip Sousa Recipient for Outstanding Band Direction, and other awards and honoraria.
The William D. Revelli Papers provide unique possibilities for research on the history of teaching at the University of Michigan. The Revelli papers, covering the years 1960-1992, are arranged into six record series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; University of Michigan Activities; Other Professional Activities; Visual Materials; and Audio Cassettes.
Subjects:
Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-1994.; Bands (Music)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Conductors (Music)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Marching bands--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Instruction and study--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Band.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-1994.; Bands.; Marching bands.; Revelli Hall (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Band.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series (Box 1) begins with a look at Revelli's career through newspaper clippings. There is a copy of Revelli's reflections of his long, illustrious career as a band director/musician. Researchers can read materials that pertain to Revelli's personal life, from his first directing position at Hobart High School, through to his retirement as the University of Michigan's band director in 1971.
  - Biographical
    - Manuscript, "William D. Revelli: The Hobart Band," by George C. Cavanaugh 1969 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1935-1994, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Reflections by Revelli undated (Box 1)
    - Revelli birthplace (Spring Gulch, Colorado) (Box 1)
  - Personal
    - Hobart High School Band 1920s (Box 1)
    - Aurora, Indiana Yearbook 1929 (Box 1)
    - Hobart High School Band Yearbook 1929 (Box 1)
    - Silver Anniversary 1960 (Box 1)
    - 25th Anniversary Friendship Book 1960 (Box 1)
    - Retirement 1971 (Box 1)
    - Awards 1956-1991 (Box 1)
      (see also proclamations in box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1921-1994
  The Correspondence series (Box 2) is arranged alphabetically by correspondent with separate files for "Band Associations" and "University of Michigan." The series spans the years from 1921 to 1994. Letters from former President Gerald Ford, and former Alabama Governor George Wallace are included.
  - A-B, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Band Associations (Box 1)
  - C-G, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Giannini, Vittorio (Box 1)
  - Ginastera, Alberto (Box 1)
  - Goldman, Edwin Franko, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Goldman Room (Box 1)
  - Gould, Morton (Box 1)
  - Grainger, Percy (Box 1)
  - H (Box 1)
  - I-T, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Band 1961-1994 (Box 2)
  - V-Z, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous and unfiled
- University of Michigan Activities
  The University of Michigan Activities series (Box 3) focuses on the University of Michigan Marching, and Symphony Bands. From Band Day material, to contracts for touring, to the East European and Soviet Union Tour of 1961, and the European Tour of 1971, this is a valuable research series.
  - Marching Band
    - Professorship Status 1937 (Box 3)
    - Band/Orchestra Association circa 1937-1942 (Box 3)
    - Band Day 1949 (Box 3)
    - Band Contracts 1950s (Box 3)
    - Band Membership Roster (Alumni) 1951 (Box 3)
    - Band Contacts circa 1955-1958 (Box 3)
    - Band 1970 (Box 3)
  - Symphony
    - Symphony Band 1964 (Box 3)
  - Tours
    - Symphony Band, Near Eastern/Soviet Union Tour 1961 (Box 3)
    - Symphony Band, European Tour 1971 (Box 3)
- Other Professional Activities
  Other Professional Activities (Box 3-5) is the fourth series in the Revelli Papers. Clinics and Writings comprise a large part of this series, the largest of the Revelli Papers. Here the researcher will find a survey of wind instrument literature by Revelli. Revelli wrote brief march compositions, a faculty research project entitled "International Band Instrumentation," and various articles written between 1938-1990. There is one folder of articles (1938-1956) written for the music magazine Etude in this series. Festival of Music programs (1982-1989), International Band programs (miscellaneous years), and the Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association programs are found in this series. The Band Conductors Conferences files are also included in the series. The series covers the years 1949-1966. Researchers will find valuable information on the history of a band organization in this series.
  - Band Conductors Conference, 10 folders
    - 1949-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1955 (Box 3)
    - 1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1963 (Box 3)
    - 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
  - Clinics
    - Revelli International School for Bands (Switzerland) 1974 (Box 4)
    - Florida A&M clinic 1977 (Box 4)
    - U.S. Army Band-International Band Clinic 1986 (Box 4)
    - Southeastern United States Honor Band 1991 (Box 4)
    - Various clinics (Box 4)
  - Writings
    - 1934 (Box 4)
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1938-1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Band composer biographies (Box 5)
    - CMI Music World Magazine 1971-1974 (Box 5)
    - Composer contract 1981 (Box 5)
    - Conducting/Music Interpretation Strategies undated (Box 5)
    - Etude articles, circa 1938-1956 (Box 5)
    - Marching band techniques, 2 pamphlets (Box 5)
    - "Revelli Editions," music scores (Box 5)
    - School instrumental music program 1960 (Box 5)
    - Survey of wind instrument and percussion literature, 2 pamphlets (Box 5)
    - World of Music Band Course 1939 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan Programs
    - University of Michigan 1937-1973, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Programs
    - American Bandmasters Association (ABA), various years (Box 5)
    - College Band Directors National Association (CBDNA), various years, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Festival of Music 1982-1989 (Box 5)
    - International Band, various years (Box 5)
    - Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association, various years (Box 5)
    - National Band Association (NBA), various years (Box 5)
    - Sudler Cup, various years (Box 5)
  - Playbills/proclamations
    - Playbills (Box 5)
    - Oversize Playbills (Box 9)
    - Proclamations (Box 5)
    - Oversize Proclamations (Box 9)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series is comprised of photographs and motion pictures. Many of the photographs concern the University of Michigan Marching, Symphony, and Alumni bands, in practice or in concert. From Rose Bowl appearances (1947-1949), the Eastern European/Soviet Union Symphonic Band Tour (1961), to the ground breaking ceremonies of Revelli Hall (1973), the photograph series documents interesting facets of Revelli the man and the maestro. Some of the photographs are oversized, including photographs of Hill Auditorium, and a portrait of the American composer/conductor Percy Granger. The most interesting oversized item is a copy of the Alfred Eisenstadt photograph of drum major Dick Smith in 1950 for LIFE Magazine magazine. A video tape and slides are also included in the Visual Materials series.
  Films also comprise a segment of this series (Box 8). There are thirteen films, eight black and white films, and five color films. All films are silent. Each film documents performances of the University of Michigan Marching Band. The twelfth film, taken at UCLA and at Michigan State University, is of particular interest. It provides a good shot of Revelli conducting the University of Michigan Band.
  - Photographs
    (see oversize items in box 9)
    - University of Michigan
      - Bowl Appearances 1947-1949 (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, historical undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band 1914 (Box 6)
      - Marching Band practices undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Marching Band 1964 (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, Band Day undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, "Script" messages undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, "Block M," undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, Alumni undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, University of Minnesota stadium undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band, various stadiums undated (Box 6)
      - Marching Band Drum Majors (Box 6)
    - Tours
      - Symphony Band, Near Eastern/Soviet Union Tour 1961, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Symphony Band, European Tour 1971 (Box 6)
      - Symphony Band, European Tours, various years (Box 6)
      - Symphony Band (Box 9)
    - Symphony Band undated (Box 6)
    - Conducting, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Appearances, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Portraits (Box 6)
    - Personal (Box 6)
      (early and mid-career; portraits and informal shots)
    - Awards, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "The Victors" (Box 6)
    - Revelli Hall (Box 9)
    - Revelli with Others, 11 folders (Box 7)
    - Associations, 12 folders (Box 7)
    - Copy of Eisenstadt Photo
      - "Dick Smith, Drum Major," by Alfred Eisenstadt May 31, 1950 Ferry Field, LIFE Magazine (Box 9)
    - Negatives undated (Box 7)
    - Slides
      - 1961 (Box 7)
      - 1967 (Box 7)
      - Tray undated (Box 7)
  - Films
    - University of Michigan Marching Band
      - Band Day, 1956-Northwestern game, color, silent, ca. 6 min. (Box 8)
        (Half-time, first UM band only, shots of high school bands in stand, then footage of mass bands marching on fields.)
      - Indiana circa 1954, b/w, silent, ca. 5 min. (Box 8)
        (Heart pierced by arrow, church?, house?)
      - Indiana 1956, color, silent, ca. 7 min. (Box 8)
        (Some ground level shots, brief close-up of Revelli conducting, horse and wagon, person scratching head, spell-out "Team.")
      - Iowa, Minnesota, Northwestern, and Ohio bands undated (Box 8)
        (Grandfather clock, Christmas tree, and MN band forms Little Brown Jug)
      - Marching Band 1946, color, silent, ca. 5 min. (Box 8)
      - Marching Band at Ohio State 1952, b/w, silent, ca. 4 min. (Box 8)
        (Stick figure in "black face?")
      - Marching Band at Northwestern 1954, color, silent, ca. 7 min. (Box 8)
        (Person, horse and sleigh, also some of NW band)
      - Marching Band at Ohio State 1954, b/w, silent, ca. 6 min. (Box 8)
        (Dragon, rocket, dancers)
      - Michigan State 1950, b/w, silent, ca. 8 min. (Box 8)
        (Hawaiian War Chant?, hula dancer. boat, some game footage)
      - Pennsylvania 1953, b/w, silent, ca. 5 min. (Box 8)
        (Soldier, woman, teapot?, camel?)
      - Small reel circa 1956, b/w, silent, ca. 3 min. (Box 8)
        (UM band, anchor and ship, Navy ROTC unit?)
      - UCLA, and Michigan State undated, color, silent, ca. 8 min. (Box 8)
        (Good shot of Revelli conducting, formation of player punting football)
      - Washington 1953, b/w, silent, ca. 7 min. (Box 8)
        (Elaborate "M")
    - Videotape (VHS) 1990 (Box 8)
- Sound cassette tapes
  The last series in the Revelli Papers is the Audio Cassette series (Box 7). It has eleven audio cassette tapes some of which contain Revelli's reflections on his long career as a conductor, from Hobart High School, to his own personal interests.
  - Miscellaneous unprocessed, 11 audiocassettes (Box 10)